<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>University Of Oxford on BBSRC Bistability of Cell Cycle Transitions Project</title>
    <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/universities/university-of-oxford/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in University Of Oxford on BBSRC Bistability of Cell Cycle Transitions Project</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/universities/university-of-oxford/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>bela_novak</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/bela_novak/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/bela_novak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bela Novak trained as a biochemical engineer and started his research career as an experimental cell biologist working on the fission yeast cell cycle with Prof. Murdoch Mitchison. In the early nineties, in collaboration with Prof. John Tyson, he pioneered a systems-level description of eukaryotic cell cycle controls. The mathematical modelling approach that he established, based on biochemical reaction kinetics, computer simulations and dynamical systems theory, has proven effective in bridging the gap between molecular control networks and cell physiology. In his hands, these models proved successful in uncovering basic principles and molecular mechanisms of cell cycle control. Being well-versed in the experimental literature, he easily communicates with experimentalists, evidenced by his joint Cell and Nature publications with Dr Frank Uhlmann (CRUK, LRI) and Dr Wolfgang Zachariae (MPI, Martinsried) on the budding yeast cell cycle and meiosis. Recently, he has started successful collaborations with four experimentalists participating in this proposal (Prof. Francis Barr, Dr Helfrid Hochegger, Dr Ulrike Gruneberg and Dr Chris Bakal), which also led to publications in Molecular Cell and PloS Genetics&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>charlotte_smith</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/charlotte_smith/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/charlotte_smith/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Charlotte Smith has worked for the University of Oxford since 2004. She has worked in finance and management roles at the Doctoral Training Centre and the Oxford Centre for Integrative Systems Biology (OCISB). Recently she has been working with departments across the Medical Sciences Division on Athena SWAN processes. For the Bistability of Cell Cycle Transitions project Charlotte works in a part-time project management role.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>francis_barr</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/francis_barr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/francis_barr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Francis Barr is a cell biologist and biochemist working on the regulation of cell growth and division events. As a postdoctoral fellow with Graham Warren he identified new structural proteins of the Golgi apparatus that explain its profound structural rearrangements during the cell cycle. He has gone on to carry out ground-breaking studies on the role of Rab GTPases and their regulators in membrane trafficking. He demonstrated the function of Rab8 in primary cilium formation in human cells, and the molecular basis of altered membrane trafficking in human diseases including Hermansky Pudlak Syndrome, Geroderma Osteodyplastica, and Warburg Micro Syndrome. Barr’s work on cell cycle control of membrane trafficking processes has extended to the events leading up to cytokinesis. His work demonstrated that mammalian cells regulate cytokinesis by a novel mitotic kinesin MKlp2 required to transport Aurora B from centromeres to the central spindle at the onset of anaphase. Subsequently, he has shown how the key Aurora B substrate KIF4A regulates microtubule dynamics during anaphase central spindle length control. Barr also identified the mechanism controlling Plk1 localisation in human cells during anaphase, and showed that the key Plk1 substrate controlling the timing of abscission in cytokinesis is the Cep55 membrane-remodelling factor. His latest work has focused on the identification of regulatory phosphatases for the Plk1-PRC1 complex in anaphase. Together with Bela Novak he has developed an experimentally validated model explaining why cell cleavage initiates only after sister chromatid separation has occurred. In collaboration with Dr Gruneberg, he has shown how protein phosphatase 6 regulates the Aurora A kinase in mitosis, and how alterations to this enzyme may promote cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lukas_hutter</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/lukas_hutter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/lukas_hutter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a DPhil student in my third year and working on the meta/ana transition and mitotic exit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>scott_rata</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/scott_rata/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/scott_rata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a fourth-year DPhil student, modelling the G2/M transition with Helfrid Hochegger&amp;rsquo;s group. We are investigating the factors that contribute to the triggering and to the hysteresis of this transtion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research interests also include the metaphase-to-anaphase transition, modelling the regulation of separase and its effects on the localisation of the chromosomal passenger complex.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>stefan_heldt</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/stefan_heldt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/stefan_heldt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stefan Heldt studied &lt;strong&gt;Biosystems Engineering&lt;/strong&gt; at the Otto von Guericke University in Magdeburg, Germany. He received his degree in 2009 after completing a diploma thesis on stochastic simulations of mRNA translation in the group of Prof. Celso Grebogi at the University of Aberdeen, Scotland. He then joined the Max Planck Institute for Dynamics of Complex Technical Systems for a Ph.D. developing mechanistic, multi-scale models of influenza virus infection. This work awarded him the 2016 MTZ Award for Medical Systems Biology. Since 2015, he is a postdoctoral research fellow in Bela Novak’s lab, where he uses mathematical modelling to understand the dynamic characteristics of the mammalian cell cycle and its regulation. In this project, he is working closely with Alexis Barr from Chris Bakal’s lab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ulrike_gruneberg</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/ulrike_gruneberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/ulrike_gruneberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ulrike Gruneberg is a Senior Medical Research Fellow at the Sir William Dunn School of Pathology in Oxford. Ulrike received her postdoctoral training in the labs of Elmar Schiebel and Erich Nigg and was subsequently awarded a prestigious Cancer Research UK Career Development Fellowship to start her own lab, initially at the University of Liverpool and then at the University of Oxford. Ulrike’s lab studies the mechanisms that regulate spindle formation and chromosome segregation in mammalian cells. In particular, Ulrike is interested in understanding the process of the metaphase-to-anaphase transition and the regulatory mechanisms that control this cell cycle transition. Questions that are studied in the lab are how stable microtubule-kinetochore interactions are formed, how the spindle assembly checkpoint is activated and silenced and how dynamic post-translational modifications such as phosphorylation and acetylation control these cell cycle events. Ulrike uses a combination of cell biological and biochemical techniques to address these questions, and the lab has extensive expertise in the generation and use of fluorescently tagged stable cell lines to study cell cycle progression by live cell imaging, as well as the implementation of biochemical and immunofluorescence based screens to identify novel regulators of cell cycle progression.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>