<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BBSRC Bistability of Cell Cycle Transitions Project</title>
    <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on BBSRC Bistability of Cell Cycle Transitions Project</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DNA damage during S-phase mediates the proliferation- 2 quiescence decision in the subsequent G1 via p21 expression (Under Revision)</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/barr_naturecommunications_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/barr_naturecommunications_2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>December 2016 Project Meeting</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/news/December_2016_Project_Meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/news/December_2016_Project_Meeting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our annual project meeting was held in Keble College, Oxford and included two days of project updates, scientific presentations and sharing ideas. The presentations were divided into four sessions and all the groups joined in the animated discussions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post80&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/2016DecGroupPhoto.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;BiCycle Project Meeting December 2016, Keble College, Oxford&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Bistable Switches Govern M Phase Entry</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/mochida_currbiol_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/mochida_currbiol_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A PP2A-B55 recognition signal controls substrate dephosphorylation kinetics during mitotic exit</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/cundell_jcb_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/cundell_jcb_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interviews with Prof. Novak (in Hungarian)</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/news/June_2016_BelaInterview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/news/June_2016_BelaInterview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While on a visit to Budapest in May 2016, Bela Novak was interviewed for two Hungarian publications,. The interviews in Hungarian are available here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sciencemeetup.444.hu/2016/06/11/a-biologusok-sokszor-a-lehetetlent-varjak-a-modellezotol&#34;&gt;Interview with the Budapest Science Meetup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/pdf/Interview_BelaNovak.pdf&#34;&gt;Article in the Hungarian Chemical Journal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bistability of mitotic entry and exit switches during open mitosis in mammalian cells</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/hegarat_bioessays_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/hegarat_bioessays_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nutritional Control of Cell Size by the Greatwall-Endosulfine-PP2A·B55 Pathway</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/chica_currbiol_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/chica_currbiol_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Dynamical Framework for the All-or-None G1/S Transition</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/barr_cellsystems_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/barr_cellsystems_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper published in Cell Systems</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/news/2016_CellSystems_Paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/news/2016_CellSystems_Paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major publication from the Bicycle project is helping to reveal how mammalian cells control transition into the DNA replication phase of the cell cycle. The research published in Cell Systems (1) comes from the ongoing collaboration between the labs of Bela Novak (Oxford) and Chris Bakal (ICR), who are investigators on the Bicycle project together with Francis Barr, Ulrike Gruneberg and Helfrid Hochegger. Postdocs Alexis Barr at the ICR and Stefan Heldt in Oxford are responsible for much of the work carried out for this paper. The research provides a molecular explanation for how mammalian cells transition abruptly and irreversibly into the DNA replication phase. It also provides insight into how other transitions in the cell cycle may be controlled.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post80&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/publication/barr_cellsystems_2016_1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cells control DNA replication through an elaborate set of networks that are similar between yeast and mammalian cells. There are two distinct points that the cell must pass through to enter S-phase (DNA replication phase). The decision to proliferate takes place during the resting (G1) phase of the cell cycle - at &amp;lsquo;Start&amp;rsquo; in yeast or the &amp;lsquo;restriction point&amp;rsquo; in mammalian cells. The irreversible transition from G1- to S-phase and commitment to replication occurs shortly afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyclins are a family of proteins that are important for driving the cell into S-phase. By forming complexes with the Cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs), Cyclins promote the activation of CDK activity. Different combinations of Cdk/Cyclins control different transitions within the cell cycle, and the G1/S transition is driven by the activity of Cdk2, in complex with either CyclinE or CyclinA. These Cyclins accumulate as their genes are turned on at the restriction point. However, full activation of Cdk2:Cyclin complexes first requires degradation of Cdk inhibitors (CKIs), such as the p27 protein, which keeps Cyclin:CDK complexes in an inactive state. On top of these controls are feedback loops that ensure that the G1/S transition is both abrupt and irreversible. The dynamic interactions between these different cell cycle components have been well described in yeast but are less well understood in more complex mammalian cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The G1/S transition is one of four cell cycle transition points being studied using systems biology approaches as part of the collaborative Bicycle project. As a starting point, the Novak and Bakal groups decided to use HeLa cells to study this transition. Like many cancer cells, HeLa cells do not have an intact restriction point and enter into S-phase directly after cell division. The cells therefore provide an excellent model for studying the G1/S transition. In addition, the G1/S transition is an attractive therapeutic target for preventing cancer cells from dividing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post80&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/publication/barr_cellsystems_2016_2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Images of HeLa cells expressing p27 reporter (green). The image shows stills taken from a movie of this cell going through the cell cycle. The cell starts in G2 (no p27), enters mitosis (round cell), divides into two daughter cells (dumb-bell shape) and both daughter cells enter G1. During G1, daughter cells start to express and accumulate p27, which is then rapidly degraded immediately prior to S-phase entry.Up to now, researchers have studied the mammalian cell cycle using synchronized cell populations. The new research uniquely takes a single cell approach, measuring the levels of key regulatory components of G1/S by imaging cells using confocal microscopy. A high-throughput automated system in the Bakal lab allows multiple samples to be imaged at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Single cell analysis is one of the key parts of this study, and it was vital that we took the time to generate and validate the cell cycle reporters, which is technically the most challenging element,&amp;rsquo; says postdoc Alexis Barr. Generating these reporters allowed her to image and measure two components in any one cell at the same time and by linking back to a common component, correlate the expression and activity of the key components. To handle the huge amount of data generated, the group also had to develop a semi-automated image analysis pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Barr constructed reporters for the Cdk inhibitor p27 and for CyclinA and CyclinE, which form complexes with Cdk2 and activate it, triggering entry into S-phase. She also made a reporter of Cdk2 activity and used PCNA, a component of the DNA replication machinery, as a marker of DNA replication. Once the group had collected the data, they had to average the time-courses for each of the reporters and align the cells to the start of DNA replication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Novak explains what they saw: &amp;lsquo;When you do this, you see a precipitous drop in p27 levels. It&amp;rsquo;s like going to the edge of the cliff and dropping off.&amp;rsquo; Once CyclinE reached a critical level, p27 could not exist anymore and displayed a very sharp, switch-like drop just as replication started. The genes for both CyclinA and CyclinE are switched on in a similar way, but CyclinA is degraded during G1 so CyclinE accumulates first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how the activities of the different cell cycle components are related, Professor Novak and his postdocs used the experimental data as they were being generated to develop a dynamic model. Because each cell is different and &amp;lsquo;noisy&amp;rsquo;, they needed to carry out stochastic modeling. They were able to construct a model of the G1/S transition that suggested that the abrupt degradation of p27 is due to a feedback loop between Cdk2:CyclinE and p27 and that this drives a switch-like entry into S-phase.  Dynamics of the G1/S transition in HeLa cells. Time-courses for each of the cell cycle components as measured in single cells was averaged across all cells and aligned to S-phase entry (time zero).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their model also predicted the impact of another cell cycle component, Emi1, on the G1/S transition: that Emi1 was important in ensuring that the G1/S transition was irreversible. Dr Barr tested this by depleting cells of Emi1 using RNAi and found that, as predicted, G1/S control was lost and cells underwent additional rounds of DNA replication.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post80&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/publication/barr_cellsystems_2016_3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Professor Novak explains that an important feature of the G1/S switch is that, like a light switch, it is a bistable switch; it has critical points where it is turned on and off and is &amp;lsquo;cleaner&amp;rsquo; than other types of switches. The demonstration, both experimentally and theoretically, that a bistable switch seen in yeast is also present in more complex mammalian cells is a key finding of the research. &amp;lsquo;We want to understand what types of switches are operating in the mammalian cell cycle. Now we&amp;rsquo;ve used single cells to show for the first time that a bistable switch is operating for G1/S, controlling the activation of Cdk2 by Cyclin E and p27.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having focused on cancer cells in this study, the group is now looking at normal cells. The presence of a restriction point in these cells makes the work far more challenging but equally important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Barr puts much of the group&amp;rsquo;s success down to the excellent communication between its members despite their diverse scientific backgrounds. &amp;lsquo;We discuss work at least once a week and sometimes every day. This helps us to understand each other&amp;rsquo;s work and technical problems. As a biologist or mathematician, we make assumptions in our work and it&amp;rsquo;s good to be able to challenge these.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting about the novel use of a single cell imaging approach, Dr Bakal says: &amp;ldquo;We know a lot about the cell cycle from work done mostly in populations, but barely any work has been done in single human cells. Looking at the single cell versus a population is the approach of the future - we have the potential to learn many things about the cell cycle, as well as challenge what we think we know already.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He highlights a further importance of the work. &amp;lsquo;The mathematical models that we&amp;rsquo;re building will allow us to find the true points of interventions in cancer cells and design small molecules to target these. By providing us with maps, we will know where in the pathway to strike – up to now, we&amp;rsquo;ve been guessing this.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bicycle project is funded by BBSRC via the sLoLa research initiative, grant reference number BB/M00354X/1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/barr_cellsystems_2016/&#34;&gt;More details on the publication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Premature Sister Chromatid Separation Is Poorly Detected by the Spindle Assembly Checkpoint as a Result of System-Level Feedback</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/mirkovic_cellreports_2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/mirkovic_cellreports_2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Models in biology: lessons from modeling regulation of the eukaryotic cell cycle</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/tyson_bmcbiology_2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/tyson_bmcbiology_2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model scenarios for switch-like mitotic transitions</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/pk_febsletters_2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/publication/pk_febsletters_2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>December 2014 Project Meeting</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/news/December_2014_Project_Meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/news/December_2014_Project_Meeting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our first project meeting took place on the first official day of the grant, 1st December 2014. The meeting was held in the Department of Biochemistry in Oxford and involved all the project groups and representatives from project partner GSK.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post80&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/2014DecGroupPhoto.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;BiCycle Project Meeting December 2014, Biochemistry, Oxford&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code and Computational Resources</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/resource/code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/resource/code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Test, Test&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our Research</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/research/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;our-research&#34;&gt;Our Research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During its growth and division cycle the cell replicates all of its components and distributes them to create two daughter cells [1]. It is essential that the underlying processes, DNA replication (S phase), mitosis (M phase) and cell division (CD), take place in a defined sequence with the correct temporal separation: G1 → S → G2 → M → CD → G1 → . Progression through this sequence is characterized by specific transitions at boundaries between sequential stages of the cell cycle. At the &lt;strong&gt;Restriction point&lt;/strong&gt; in G1 phase the cell decides whether to proliferate or quiesce (G0). This is followed later by the abrupt &lt;strong&gt;G1/S transition&lt;/strong&gt; into S phase (DNA replication). Post-replicative cells in G2 phase enter into mitosis (M phase) at the &lt;strong&gt;G2/M transition&lt;/strong&gt;. The decision to segregate sister-chromatids once all have become aligned pairwise on the mitotic spindle takes place at the end of prometaphase and triggers the &lt;strong&gt;meta/anaphase transition and cytokinesis&lt;/strong&gt;. Anaphase is followed by the exit from mitosis back into G1 (mitotic exit). Progression through the cell cycle in eukaryotes is controlled by a conserved protein interaction network composed of protein kinases and phosphatases with stoichiometric inhibitors and activators, transcription factors, ubiquitin-conjugating enzymes and the proteasome. The molecular interactions among these cell cycle regulators create a complicated &lt;strong&gt;dynamical system&lt;/strong&gt; that oscillates once per cell cycle. In our proposal we focus on a systems-level description of the major cell cycle transitions in the mammalian cell cycle. Our &lt;strong&gt;hypothesis-driven&lt;/strong&gt; research is based on our theoretical investigations of generic dynamic characteristics in eukaryotic cell cycle transitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/activator-inhibitor.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fig.1: Generic network motif of cell cycle transitions&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;The three components are embedded in a negative feedback loop. The antagonism between Activator&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; and Inhibitor&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; creates a positive circuit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progression through each of the cell cycle transitions is controlled by a balance between &lt;strong&gt;inhibitors&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;activators&lt;/strong&gt; (Fig.1). Before each cell cycle transition, an inhibitor overwhelms the activator responsible for the transition (refered here as &lt;strong&gt;Inhibitor&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Activator&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). During the transition Inhibitor&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; gets down-regulated by the activator of the previous cell cycle stage (Activator&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;) which leads to activation of Activator&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;. However after the transition, Activator&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; inhibits the activator characteristic for the earlier cell cyle stage (Activator&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;), which creates a &lt;strong&gt;negative feedback loop&lt;/strong&gt; in the network [2]. The &lt;strong&gt;irreversibility&lt;/strong&gt; of cell cycle transitions requires that Inhibitor&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; is kept inactive in the post-transition state despite the disappearance of Activator&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;. We argue that the irreversibility of the cell cycle transition is achieved by an &lt;strong&gt;antagonistic interaction&lt;/strong&gt; between Activator&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; and its cognate Inhibitor&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;. This &lt;strong&gt;double-negative feedback&lt;/strong&gt; makes the post-transition state and Activator&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; self-maintaining by creating a &lt;strong&gt;bistable switch&lt;/strong&gt; (Fig.2). The irreversible switch creates a &lt;strong&gt;‘point of no return’&lt;/strong&gt; in the cell cycle transition, which can be experimentally tested by the following protocol. In a partly synchronised cell population undergoing the transition, abrupt inactivation of Activatori-1 redirects cells back to the bistable region close to the y-axis. The future cellular fate will be dependent upon whether cells end up above or below the unstable saddle point (Fig.3). Cells early in the transition will return to the pre-transition cell cycle state (cell ) with low Activator&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; and high Inhibitor&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; levels. In contrast, cells later in the transition will manage to reach the post-transition (i) state (cell ) where the levels of Activator&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; and Inhibitor&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; are the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/phaseplane.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fig.2: Two phaseplane portraits of the generic cell cycle switch&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;At small Activator&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt; levels the network has two alternative steady states (solid lines) separated by unstable saddle points (dashed lines). The trajectories are shown by dotted curves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sequential connection of these switch-like network motifs not only accounts for oscillations of activators and inhibitors during cell cycle progression, but also provides &lt;strong&gt;‘checkpoint’&lt;/strong&gt; control over the cell cycle transitions. By monitoring defective states of chromosomes (damaged, not fully replicated, or improperly aligned on the mitotic spindle), intracellular surveillance mechanisms keep Activator&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt; at a subthreshold level and thereby block the transition. When the defect is repaired, the bistable switch is released to drive the transition as shown (Fig.2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/bistability.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fig.3: The bistable switch creates a ‘point of no return’&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Depletion of the initial activator (Activator&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;) during the transition bifurcates the cell population.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our view of eukaryotic cell cycle control is based on years of experience modelling the cell cycle of organisms like budding [3] and fission [4] yeasts, Xenopus [5] and Drosophila [6] embryos. Our prediction that eukaryotic cell cycle transitions are controlled by underlying bistable network motifs has been tested and confirmed experimentally (by the research groups of Cross, Ferrell, Sible, Morgan and Uhlmann) for each cell cycle transition of lower eukaryotes (yeasts and Xenopus embryos). However it remains elusive, whether these same &lt;strong&gt;design principles&lt;/strong&gt; are applicable to higher eukaryotic cells with more complex cell cycle control networks. Although there is strong evidence for the universality of eukaryotic cell cycle components, the physiological characteristics of the cell cycle vary widely across cell types. This raises the question whether the control mechanisms are conserved or not? A systematic analysis of bistable and other network motifs in mammalian cell cycle transitions is essential to address this question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our working hypothesis, mammalian cell cycle progression is driven by a &lt;strong&gt;series of bistable switches&lt;/strong&gt; connected in a linear sequence (Fig.4). The activators of early cell cycle transitions (from the Restriction Point to the G2/M transition) belong to the Cyclin-dependent protein-kinase (&lt;strong&gt;Cdk&lt;/strong&gt;) family (Cdk1, Cdk2, Cdk4, Cdk6 etc.) in complex with their regulatory &lt;strong&gt;Cyclin&lt;/strong&gt; subunits (Cyclin-A, -B, -D, -E etc.). During the cell cycle, Cdks are periodically associated with their activating Cyclins whose levels are determined by transcription factors (e.g. E2F) and degradation machineries (ubiquitin-ligases: SCF and APC/C). The activity of Cdk:Cyclin complexes is subject to additional controls by stoichiometric Cdk inhibtors (e.g. p27&lt;sup&gt;Kip1&lt;/sup&gt;), inhibitory phosphorylations modulated by Wee1-kinases and Cdc25-phosphatases. The different activators and inhibitors of mammalian cell cycle transitions are summarised in the Table and the experimental evidence for potential bistable network motifs operating at cell cycle transitions are briefly summarised below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;img-post&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/img/motif.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fig.4: The sequential activation of bistable switches during mammalian cell cycle progression&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;The antagonistic relationships between cell cycle activators and inhibitors are illustrated as an auto-activation of activators, for simplicity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Restriction Point (RP)&lt;/strong&gt; is enforced by the Retinoblastoma Protein (pRb), a repressor of E2F transcription factors. pRb is inactivated by CycE-dependent kinase via a positive feedback loop:
E2F → CycE
 ¬ Rb ¬ E2F. The RP is the only cell cycle transition in mammalian cells where bistability has been experimentally demonstrated [7].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;G1/S transition&lt;/strong&gt; is triggered by CycE-kinase which turns off degradation of CycA by APC/C&lt;sup&gt;Cdh1&lt;/sup&gt; and promotes degradation of the Cdk2 inhibitor p27&lt;sup&gt;Kip1&lt;/sup&gt; (double-negative feedback). CycE levels are down-regulated after the transition by activities of Cdk2 (negative feedback) [8,9].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;G2/M transition&lt;/strong&gt; is facilitated by CycA-kinase turning off the degradation of CycB through inactivation of APC/CCdh1 and by reducing the extent of inhibitory phosphorylation of Cdk1:CycB complexes and PP2A:B55 activity. Once activated, CycB-kinase is able to prevent this inhibitory phosphorylation (positive feedback). CycB also promotes APC/C&lt;sup&gt;Cdc20&lt;/sup&gt; dependent destruction of CycA (negative feedback) by a SAC independent mechanism without destabilizing the mitotic state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meta/anaphase transition&lt;/strong&gt; is initiated by APC/C&lt;sup&gt;Cdc20&lt;/sup&gt; whose activation requires CycB dependent phosphorylation. APC/C&lt;sup&gt;Cdc20&lt;/sup&gt; triggers anaphase by promoting the degradation of Separase inhibitors, Securin and CycB (negative feedback). However APC/C activity is blocked by the Mitotic Checkpoint Complex (MCC) which is inactivated by APC/C dependent ubiquitylation10 (double-negative feedback).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mitotic exit&lt;/strong&gt; includes the activation of PP2A:B55 phosphatase which counteracts the inhibitory phosphorylations by Cdk1:CycB on the cytokinesis machinery. Since PP2A:B55 is kept inactive during mitosis by its stoichiometric inhibitors (Endosulfine, Arpp19) in a CycB-kinase dependent manner, its initial activation requires CycB degradation by APC/C&lt;sup&gt;Cdc20&lt;/sup&gt;. We have proposed11 that PP2A:B55 promotes its own activation by inactivating Greatwall-kinase (positive feedback).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;activators-and-inhibitors-of-mammalian-cell-cycle-transitions&#34;&gt;Activators and inhibitors of mammalian cell cycle transitions.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;row text-center&#34;&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;}
.tg .tg-naq5{font-weight:bold;font-family:&#34;Courier New&#34;, Courier, monospace !important;;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-r5us{font-family:&#34;Courier New&#34;, Courier, monospace !important;;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-naq5&#34;&gt;Cell Cycle Transition&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-naq5&#34;&gt;Inhibitors&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-naq5&#34;&gt;Activators&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Restriction point&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Retinoblastoma Protein (pRb)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Cdk4,6:CycD,Cdk2:CycE, E2F&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;G1/S&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;p27:Kip1, APC/C:Cdh1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Cdk2:CycE, Cdk2:CycA&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;G2/M&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Wee1, Myt1, PP2A:B55&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Cdk1:CycB, Cdk1:CycA, Cdc25&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Meta/Anaphase&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Mitotic Checkpoint Comples (MCC)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Anaphase Promoting Complex/Cyclosome (APC/C)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Mitotic Exit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;Cdk1:CycB, Endosulfine (Arpp19), Greatwall-kinase&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-r5us&#34;&gt;PP2A:B55, Polo-kinase, Aurora-kinases&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;funded-by-the-bbsrc-grant-number-bb-m00354x-1&#34;&gt;Funded by the BBSRC grant number BB/M00354X/1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 Morgan, D. O. The Cell Cycle: Principles of Control., (New Science Press, 2007).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 Verdugo, A., Vinod, P. K., Tyson, J. J. &amp;amp; Novak, B. Molecular mechanisms creating bistable switches at cell cycle transitions. Open biology 3, 120179, doi:10.1098/rsob.120179 (2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 Chen, K. C. et al. Kinetic analysis of a molecular model of the budding yeast cell cycle. Mol Biol Cell 11, 369-391 (2000).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 Novak, B. &amp;amp; Tyson, J. J. Modeling the control of DNA replication in fission yeast. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 94, 9147-9152 (1997).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 Novak, B. &amp;amp; Tyson, J. J. Numerical analysis of a comprehensive model of M-phase control in Xenopus oocyte extracts and intact embryos. J Cell Sci 106, 1153-1168 (1993).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 Calzone, L., Thieffry, D., Tyson, J. J. &amp;amp; Novak, B. Dynamical modeling of syncytial mitotic cycles in Drosophila embryos. Mol Syst Biol 3, 131 (2007).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 Yao, G., Lee, T. J., Mori, S., Nevins, J. R. &amp;amp; You, L. A bistable Rb-E2F switch underlies the restriction point. Nat Cell Biol 10, 476-482 (2008).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 Kalaszczynska, I. et al. Cyclin A is redundant in fibroblasts but essential in hematopoietic and embryonic stem cells. Cell 138, 352-365, doi:10.1016/j.cell.2009.04.062 (2009).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 Krek, W. et al. Negative regulation of the growth-promoting transcription factor E2F-1 by a stably bound cyclin A-dependent protein kinase. Cell 78, 161-172 (1994).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 Musacchio, A. &amp;amp; Ciliberto, A. The spindle-assembly checkpoint and the beauty of self-destruction. Nat Struct Mol Biol 19, 1059-1061, doi:10.1038/nsmb.2429 (2012).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11 Hegarat, N. et al. PP2A/B55 and Fcp1 regulate Greatwall and Ensa dephosphorylation during mitotic exit. PLoS Genet 10, e1004004, doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1004004 (2014).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>