<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Principal Investigator on BBSRC Bistability of Cell Cycle Transitions Project</title>
    <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/roles/principal-investigator/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Principal Investigator on BBSRC Bistability of Cell Cycle Transitions Project</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/roles/principal-investigator/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>helfrid_hochegger</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/helfrid_hochegger/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 15:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/helfrid_hochegger/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Helfrid Hochegger works on cell cycle control using chemical genetic, advanced microscopy and proteomic approaches. He was trained in the Nobel Prize winning lab of Tim Hunt and has spent his career investigating the function of kinases and phosphatases in the regulation of cell cycle transitions. He distinguished himself by establishing a chemical genetics system to target mitotic and interphase Cdk activity in a vertebrate cell line. This work led to a prestigious Wellcome Trust career development award to set up a laboratory at the Genome Damage and Stability Centre at the University of Sussex. His genetic analysis of cell cycle control in DT40 and mammalian cells led to a recent senior CRUK research fellowship. His cellular model systems are specifically designed to analyse Cdk1 activity thresholds at the G2/M transition, which will be extremely useful for the quantitative analysis of mitotic entry models. Furthermore he will contribute valuable expertise in live-cell imaging and in genetic manipulation of the mammalian cell cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ulrike_gruneberg</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/ulrike_gruneberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 15:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/ulrike_gruneberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ulrike Gruneberg is a Senior Medical Research Fellow at the Sir William Dunn School of Pathology in Oxford. Ulrike received her postdoctoral training in the labs of Elmar Schiebel and Erich Nigg and was subsequently awarded a prestigious Cancer Research UK Career Development Fellowship to start her own lab, initially at the University of Liverpool and then at the University of Oxford. Ulrike’s lab studies the mechanisms that regulate spindle formation and chromosome segregation in mammalian cells. In particular, Ulrike is interested in understanding the process of the metaphase-to-anaphase transition and the regulatory mechanisms that control this cell cycle transition. Questions that are studied in the lab are how stable microtubule-kinetochore interactions are formed, how the spindle assembly checkpoint is activated and silenced and how dynamic post-translational modifications such as phosphorylation and acetylation control these cell cycle events. Ulrike uses a combination of cell biological and biochemical techniques to address these questions, and the lab has extensive expertise in the generation and use of fluorescently tagged stable cell lines to study cell cycle progression by live cell imaging, as well as the implementation of biochemical and immunofluorescence based screens to identify novel regulators of cell cycle progression.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>chris_bakal</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/chris_bakal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 15:03:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/chris_bakal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chris Bakal’s contributions to biology have been to use imaging and computational methods to describe the signalling networks regulating cell shape. Specifically, the Bakal laboratory has developed the use of Quantitative Morphological Signatures (QMSs) to describe the contribution of individual genes to the regulation of single-cell shape (Bakal et al., Science 2007), automated online phenotype discovery algorithms that search through databases containing millions of images to identify novel cell shapes (Yin et al., BMC Bioinformatics 2008), algorithms to determine hits from RNAi screens based on the known physical structure of signalling networks (Kraplow et al., Nature Methods 2009), combinatorial RNAi methods to determine epistatic relationships in metazoan systems (Arias-Garcia et al., Molecular Biosystems 2012), methods to describe networks through integration of phosphoproteomic and functional genomic data (Bakal et al., Science 2008), and algorithms to model hierarchical signalling relationships from QMSs derived from combinatorial RNAi (Nir et al., Genome Research 2010). Recently the Bakal laboratory devised methods to quantify the morphological heterogeneity of populations in the context of a high-throughput genetic screen, and identified a signalling network that regulates the switch-like changes in cell shape made by melanoma cells during the metastatic process (Yin et al., Nature Cell Biology 2013). The Bakal laboratory will focus on G1/S transition and will be responsible for the live cell imaging facilities as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>francis_barr</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/francis_barr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 14:52:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/francis_barr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Francis Barr is a cell biologist and biochemist working on the regulation of cell growth and division events. As a postdoctoral fellow with Graham Warren he identified new structural proteins of the Golgi apparatus that explain its profound structural rearrangements during the cell cycle. He has gone on to carry out ground-breaking studies on the role of Rab GTPases and their regulators in membrane trafficking. He demonstrated the function of Rab8 in primary cilium formation in human cells, and the molecular basis of altered membrane trafficking in human diseases including Hermansky Pudlak Syndrome, Geroderma Osteodyplastica, and Warburg Micro Syndrome. Barr’s work on cell cycle control of membrane trafficking processes has extended to the events leading up to cytokinesis. His work demonstrated that mammalian cells regulate cytokinesis by a novel mitotic kinesin MKlp2 required to transport Aurora B from centromeres to the central spindle at the onset of anaphase. Subsequently, he has shown how the key Aurora B substrate KIF4A regulates microtubule dynamics during anaphase central spindle length control. Barr also identified the mechanism controlling Plk1 localisation in human cells during anaphase, and showed that the key Plk1 substrate controlling the timing of abscission in cytokinesis is the Cep55 membrane-remodelling factor. His latest work has focused on the identification of regulatory phosphatases for the Plk1-PRC1 complex in anaphase. Together with Bela Novak he has developed an experimentally validated model explaining why cell cleavage initiates only after sister chromatid separation has occurred. In collaboration with Dr Gruneberg, he has shown how protein phosphatase 6 regulates the Aurora A kinase in mitosis, and how alterations to this enzyme may promote cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>bela_novak</title>
      <link>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/bela_novak/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 14:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://novakgroupoxford.github.io/bicycle-hugo/member/bela_novak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bela Novak trained as a biochemical engineer and started his research career as an experimental cell biologist working on the fission yeast cell cycle with Prof. Murdoch Mitchison. In the early nineties, in collaboration with Prof. John Tyson, he pioneered a systems-level description of eukaryotic cell cycle controls. The mathematical modelling approach that he established, based on biochemical reaction kinetics, computer simulations and dynamical systems theory, has proven effective in bridging the gap between molecular control networks and cell physiology. In his hands, these models proved successful in uncovering basic principles and molecular mechanisms of cell cycle control. Being well-versed in the experimental literature, he easily communicates with experimentalists, evidenced by his joint Cell and Nature publications with Dr Frank Uhlmann (CRUK, LRI) and Dr Wolfgang Zachariae (MPI, Martinsried) on the budding yeast cell cycle and meiosis. Recently, he has started successful collaborations with four experimentalists participating in this proposal (Prof. Francis Barr, Dr Helfrid Hochegger, Dr Ulrike Gruneberg and Dr Chris Bakal), which also led to publications in Molecular Cell and PloS Genetics&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>